# 大家好 今天聽說兄弟在割蜂蜜哦 過來看一下(註︰他又是經常把「蜂蜜」和「蜜蜂」說錯，會配合一下)
Hi everyone! Somebody told me that my buddy's gonna harvest the honey today. So I come and have a look.
# 帶個安全帽
Let me put on a safety hat.
# 怕萬一
Just in case
# 蟄到臉就不好看了
It would be too embarrassing if my face got stung.
# 手臂又裸露著
And my arms are naked.
# 你看 這個是 剛開箱的哦 那麼多
Look! This is, this box is newly opened. There's so much.
# 要慢一點
You gotta do it slowly.
# 別把蜂蜜惹急了 惹急了它就蟄人了
Don't provoke the honey, the honey bees. They sting if they are provoked.
# 嗯
Um!
# 好甜啊
It's so sweet!
# 哎呀 謝謝 謝謝
Aya! Thanks, thanks!
# 哇 這一塊多哦 這個
Wa! This board is filled with honey, this one.
# 這個 要哪個 你要不要自己提
This one.
Which one? You wanna hold it yourself?
# 這個才多 我要提這個 這個多的
This is the heavy one. I wanna hold this one, the one with more honey.
# 好重啊 這個 最少幾斤 你看
It's so heavy! This is, at least a couple of kilograms. Look!
# 看到沒有
See?
# 出去出去 哎 走啦
Get out, get out! Ay! It's out.
# 你看 這就是我們本地的土蜂蜜
Look! This is the local honey here at our place.
# 這個時候是百花蜜哦
At this time of the year, it is multiflora honey.
# 就是很多種花混合在一起
That means it combines many different types of flowers.
# 你看這裡 全是糖
Look! Here, it's all honey.
# 爽啊 看看
Cool! Have a look!
# 看上去都想吃
It looks so attractive.
# 我搞一塊來吃一下
Let me take a piece and have a try.
# 你看這個 都漏啊 漏啦
Have a look here! It's drip, dripping.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 全是糖 這些地方
It's all honey, this area.
# 你看最近天氣好 它這蜂蜜產量很高哦
Look! The weather is nice recently. So the yield of the honey here is really high.
# 真想一口咬下去
I really wanna simply bite it.
# 這樣又不好
But it's not nice.
# 太粗魯啦 這樣
It's, too rude.
# 你看這邊 全是蜂蜜 看到沒有
Have a look at this side. It's all honey. See?
# 這邊也是
And this side too.
# 封了蓋的全是滿的蜜哦 封蓋了
Under the seal it's full of honey, under the seal.
# 他家的蜂蜜怎麼 那麼勤勞
Why are his honey bees, so, so diligent?
# 我們家有 有一箱蜂蜜
We also have a box of honey at home.
# 一 一滴蜜我都沒吃到
But I've never had any honey from them, not, not even a drip.
# 太懶了
They're too lazy.
# 把它甩出來
Let's spin it out.
# 甩到那個瓶子裡面裝著
Spin it out into the bucket there.
# 他把這個蓋子 蓋子要割掉 蜜才能甩得出來
The seal, he's now cutting off the seal, so that the honey can be spun out.
# 要不然甩不出來 你看 全是蜜
Otherwise, you can't spin it out. Look! It's all honey.
# 還沒甩掉 還有好多
Not yet. There's still a lot.
# 甩乾淨一點 那個蜜夠吃
Spin more thoroughly, so that we can have enough honey,
# 蜜蜂才勤快
the bees will be more diligent.
# 這一餅才重啊 哇 最少七八斤
This is the heavy board. Wa! It's at least three or four kilograms.
# 喂呦
Wayo!
# 你看 它這 這邊也很多哦 你看這裡
Look! Here it, there's also a lot on this side. Have a look here!
# 好重啊
It's so heavy.
# 拎都拎不起來
I can only barely hold it.
# 你看這種 這種蜜蜂是我們本地的小蜜蜂來的
Look! These are, these bees are our local bees here.
# 好多糖啊 太勤快啦
A lot of honey! They're just too diligent.
# 給他先 哎呦 那麼重 這個
I give it back to him first. Ayo! It's so heavy, this one.
# 他這樣一甩都甩到幾斤出來
A couple of kilograms can be spun out without too much work.
# 哇 你看 過濾一下
Wa! Look! Let's filter it.
# 過濾一下比較乾淨
It becomes cleaner after filtering.
# 你看這一桶 一百多斤哦 這個
Have a look at the bucket here. It's more than fifty kilograms, this one.
# 很快的 兩下就滿啦
It doesn't take long. It gets filled up very quickly.
# 那麼多蜂蜜
So much honey
# 你看這個 還有好多蜜的 這個可以吃的哦 這個
Have a look here. There's still a lot of honey. This is also edible, you know.
# 這種 這種
This one, like this one
# 你看這個 還有那麼多蜜 這個
Have a look at this one. There's still so much honey, this one.
# 這種蜂巢 可以 可以用來嚼一下 好香啊
This kind of bee combs, can be, can be chewed. It smells so good.
# 你看
Look!
# 嗯
Um!
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 老是往地下掉
It's always dripping onto the ground.
# 這就是蜂巢蜜
This is called honeycomb.
# 其實蜂巢也可以吃的
Bee combs are also edible, in fact.
# 嗯~
Um~
# 這好多
Here's a lot!
# 你看 這裡還有好多啊
Look! Here are still a lot!
# 幾十箱 上百箱
Tens, or up to a hundred boxes
# 兄弟家的小別墅
This is my buddy's tiny villa.
# 還有一條狗在這裡
Here's also a dog.
# 你看 兄弟的大狗
Look! My buddy's big dog.
# 好猛啊
He's ferocious.
# 上上上去
Go, go, get him!
# 幹他幹他幹他
Attack, attack, attack!
# 那鏈子 鏈子一脫的話 麻 麻煩了 它那鏈子一脫
The chain, if the chain breaks, game, game over, if the chain breaks.
# 不聽話
Not listening.
# 它不聽話
He's not listening.
# 上面還有好多啊 一直上去都有的
Here's still a lot up there, all the way up there.
# 全是野蜂蜜哦
All is wild honey.
# 你看這些小蜜蜂 好勤勞哦
Have a look at these little bees. They're so diligent,
# 飛來飛去 飛來飛去的
flying here and there, here and there.
# 回來的時候都有花粉在腳上
There's pollen on their feet when they come back,
# 沾著 等下它拿回去就是要釀蜜
sticking there. The bees are gonna make the honey when they're back.
# 你看 腳上都有花粉的
Look! There's pollen on their feet.
# 有幾個蜜蜂虎視眈眈的看著我
Some bees are staring at me with greed.
# 喜歡看著我 等下我去吃你的蜜
They like staring at me. Your honey will be mine very soon.
# 你滿 滿箱的哦 一整箱都是
This is full, this box is full, full of honey.
# 你看 腳上都有 花粉
Look! There's pollen, on their feet.
# 飛進飛出 飛進飛出
In and out and in and out
# 一個禮拜左右就把糖搞滿啦
The whole box will be filled with honey in around a week.
# 哇 全部是滿的 怪不得它們不出去
Wa! It's all full. No wonder they're not going out.
# 你看 原來是 都夠吃啦 它們就不出去
Look! It's because, they have enough food. So they're not going out.
# 哇 全部滿蜜的
Wa! It's full of honey!
# 看到嗎
See?
# 滿糖的
It's complete filled with honey!
# 哇
Wa!
# 怎麼樣
How's it?
# 漏啦漏啦
It's dripping, it's dripping!
# 現在越來越多蜂蜜了哇
It's getting more and more honey bees.
# 你看 全部都圍著我了 走了
Look! They're all flying around me. Let's go.